<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook ID="ddi2-0d4d3640-9f16-013e-fb1b-02420a1c0304-nhis_00002.dat-nhis.ipums.org" version="2.5" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an Integrated Health Interview Series Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'nhis_00002.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-0d4d3640-9f16-013e-fb1b-02420a1c0304-nhis_00002.dat-nhis.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2025-11-09">November 9, 2025</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract nhis_00002.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2025-11-09">November 9, 2025</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="nhis">IPUMS NHIS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D071.V8.1</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2025-11-09"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Core Demographic Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Condition Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">High Cholesterol Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Hypertension Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Smoking Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Physical Activity Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Fatigue Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Mortality Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2438">
        <timePrd date="2015" event="single">2015</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  2015 NHIS
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="yes"><![CDATA[The Public Health Service Act (Section 308 (d)) provides that the data collected by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), may be used only for the purpose of health statistical reporting and analysis. Any effort to determine the identity of any reported case is prohibited by this law. NCHS does all it can to assure that the identity of data subjects cannot be disclosed. All direct identifiers, as well as any characteristics that might lead to identification, are omitted from the data files. Any intentional identification or disclosure of a person or establishment violates the assurances of confidentiality given to the providers of the information. 

Therefore, users will: 

Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only. 

Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director, NCHS, of any such discovery (301-458-4500). 

Not link these data files with individually identifiable data from other NCHS or non-NCHS data files. 

By using these data, you signify your agreement to comply with the above-stated statutorily-based requirements. ]]></confDec>
        <contact URI="http://www.nhis.ipums.org/" affiliation="IPUMS">Integrated Health Interview Series</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the NHIS database must cite it appropriately.  The citation is as follows:

Lynn A. Blewett, Julia A. Rivera Drew, Andrew Fenelon, Miriam L. King, Kari C.W. Williams, Daniel Backman, Etienne Breton, Grace Cooper, and Stephanie Richards. IPUMS Health Surveys: National Health Interview Survey, Version 8.1 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2025. https://doi.org/10.18128/D071.V8.1

If possible, citations should also include the URL for the NHIS site:  http://www.nhis.ipums.org.

Please see http://www.nhis.ipums.org/nhis/citation.shtml for precise formatting of the citation.]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[The Public Health Service Act (Section 308 (d)) provides that the data collected by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), may be used only for the purpose of health statistical reporting and analysis. Any effort to determine the identity of any reported case is prohibited by this law. NCHS does all it can to assure that the identity of data subjects cannot be disclosed. All direct identifiers, as well as any characteristics that might lead to identification, are omitted from the data files. Any intentional identification or disclosure of a person or establishment violates the assurances of confidentiality given to the providers of the information. 

Therefore, users must: 

Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only. 

Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director, NCHS, of any such discovery (301-458-4500). 

Not link these data files with individually identifiable data from other NCHS or non-NCHS data files. 

By using these data, you signify your agreement to comply with the above-stated statutorily-based requirements. 

Furthermore, users of NHIS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. Users must agree to the following conditions:
  
  
(1) Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only 

(2) Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director of NCHS of any such discovery (301-458-4500) 

(3) Do not link these data with individually-identifiable data from NCHS or non-NCHS data files 

(4) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use and distribute these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute them to others. 

(5) Cite the NHIS appropriately.  Publications and research reports based on the database must cite it appropriately.  Please see http://www.nhis.ipums.org/nhis/citation.shtml

(6) NHIS cannot be used to study small geographic areas.  The smallest geographical areas identified in the NHIS are regions (groups of states) and a limited number of metropolitan areas.

(7) This system provides individual-level data only.  The NHIS Data Extraction System will not produce tables. You will need to use a statistical software package, such as Stata, SAS, or SPSS, to analyze the downloaded data.  Alternatively, you may use the NHIS-SDA tabulator to produce tables online, without making a data extract.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  Revision of 00001]]></notes>
    <notes>This extract is a revision of the user's previous extract, ID 50760463.</notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>nhis_00002.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular"/>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr><var ID="YEAR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="YEAR">
  <location EndPos="4" StartPos="1" width="4"/>
  <labl>Survey year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[YEAR is a four-digit variable reporting the calendar year (e.g., 2003) the survey was conducted and the data were collected. YEAR indicates the survey year reported on the household record.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[This is a 4-digit numeric variable with 0 implied decimal places]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SERIAL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SERIAL">
  <location EndPos="10" StartPos="5" width="6"/>
  <labl>Sequential Serial Number, Household Record</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey year. The combination of YEAR and SERIAL provides a unique identifier for every household in the IPUMS NHIS database.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSERIAL is a 6-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="STRATA" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="STRATA">
  <location EndPos="14" StartPos="11" width="4"/>
  <labl>Stratum for variance estimation</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[STRATA is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable based on the NHIS sample design variables in the public use files concatenated with a sample design period indicator. STRATA represents the impact of the sample design stratification on the estimates of variance and standard errors. It is constant within a sample design period and changes between sample design periods. For analysis, researchers need to use STRATA in conjunction with PSU to account for stratification and clustering when computing variance estimates with IPUMS NHIS data.

See the User Notes on variance estimation for additional information.     

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSTRATA is a 5-digit numeric variable.

000:	Not in Universe]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PSU" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PSU">
  <location EndPos="17" StartPos="15" width="3"/>
  <labl>Primary sampling unit (PSU) for variance estimation</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PSU is the primary sampling unit variable that represents the impact of the sample design clustering on the estimates of variance and standard errors. It is constant within a sample design period and changes between sample design periods. For analysis, researchers need to use PSU in conjunction with STRATA to account for stratification and clustering when computing variance estimates with IPUMS NHIS data.  

See the User Notes on variance estimation for additional information.

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPSU is a 3-digit numeric variable.

000:	Not in Universe]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="NHISHID" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="NHISHID">
  <location EndPos="31" StartPos="18" width="14"/>
  <labl>NHIS Unique identifier, household</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[NHISHID is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey year. Using NHISHID, analysts can link IPUMS NHIS data with additional household-level data elements, from the NHIS source public use data files, that are not currently available in IPUMS.  NHISHID is a single variable constructed by concatenating multiple data elements from the NHIS source data files.  Analysts wishing to link person-level NHIS data should use the person-level linking key NHISPID.

See the user note on LINKING for instructions on how to create links between IPUMS NHIS and NHIS source data.  

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesNHISHID is a 14-character string variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="HHWEIGHT" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="HHWEIGHT">
  <location EndPos="37" StartPos="32" width="6"/>
  <labl>Household weight, final annual</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HHWEIGHT is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable based on the Final Annual Household Weight for 1997 forward and the Final Basic Weight in 1969-1996 NHIS public use files. HHWEIGHT represents the inverse probability of household selection into the sample, adjusted for non-response. For analyses using the household as the unit of analysis (e.g., how many households contained a person who needed help with activities of daily living?), researchers should use the household weight. 

Rather than using HHWEIGHT, researchers should use PERWEIGHT or SAMPWEIGHT when analyzing person-level variables or variables from the sample adult/sample child supplements from 1997 forward. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesHHWEIGHT is a 6-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="REGION" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="REGION">
  <location EndPos="39" StartPos="38" width="2"/>
  <labl>Region of residence</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[REGION reports the region of the U.S. where the housing unit containing survey participants was located.  The geographic information included in REGION was added during processing, rather than ascertained via questioning.  REGION is the smallest geographic unit identified in the IPUMS NHIS data for 1985 forward.  In 1968-1984, a limited number (under 30) of metropolitan areas were also identified (METAREA).

The four regions--Northeast, North Central/Midwest, South, and West--correspond to the U.S. regions recognized by the Census Bureau. Divisions and states included in the four regions are as follows:

Northeast:  New England Division (Maine, New Hampshire, Vermont, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and Connecticut) and Middle Atlantic Division (New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania)

North Central/Midwest: East North Central Division (Michigan, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Wisconsin) and West North Central Division (Minnesota, Iowa, Missouri, North Dakota, South Dakota, Kansas, and Nebraska)

South: South Atlantic Division (Delaware, Maryland, District of Columbia, Virginia, West Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida), East South Central Division (Kentucky, Tennessee, Mississippi, and Alabama), and West South Central Division (Texas, Arkansas, Oklahoma, and Louisiana)

West: Pacific Division (Washington, Alaska, Oregon, California, and Hawaii) and Mountain Division (Montana, Idaho, Wyoming, Colorado, New Mexico, Arizona, Utah, and Nevada). 

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Northeast</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>North Central/Midwest</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>South</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>West</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>NO DATA IN ROUND</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PERNUM" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PERNUM">
  <location EndPos="41" StartPos="40" width="2"/>
  <labl>Person number within family/household (from reformatting)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable that numbers all persons within each family or within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they appear in the original NHIS data.  PERNUM was created by IPUMS NHIS during the process of reformatting the original NHIS public use files. 

Prior to 2019, PERNUM numbers all persons within each family. Beginning in 2019, PERNUM numbers all person within a household and has a maximum of "2," as only the sample child and sample adult are identified in the original NHIS data. For more information, see the Comparability section.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="NHISPID" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="NHISPID">
  <location EndPos="57" StartPos="42" width="16"/>
  <labl>NHIS Unique Identifier, person</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[NHISPID is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each person in a given survey year.  Using NHISPID, analysts can link IPUMS NHIS data with additional data elements, from the NHIS source public use data files, that are not currently available in IPUMS.  For example, researchers can use NHISPID to link variables in IPUMS NHIS with other variables from the core NHIS files variables.  Alternatively, users may use NHISPID to link variables from IPUMS with variables from NHIS supplements that are not yet part of IPUMS NHIS. NHISPID is a single variable constructed by concatenating multiple data elements from the NHIS source data files.  

Analysts wishing to link household-level NHIS data should use the household-level linking key NHISHID.

See the user note on LINKING for instructions on how to create links between IPUMS NHIS and NHIS source data.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesNHISPID is a 16-character string variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="HHX" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="HHX">
  <location EndPos="64" StartPos="58" width="7"/>
  <labl>Household number (from NHIS)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, HHX reports the person's household number on the original NHIS data. HHX is unique within sample but only unique across samples when combined with information on year. Prior to 2019, this variable was available for all persons.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[This is a 7-digit numeric variable with 0 implied decimal places]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="FMX" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="FMX">
  <location EndPos="66" StartPos="65" width="2"/>
  <labl>Family number (from NHIS)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For all persons, FMX reports the person's family number within the household, as documented on the family record on the original NHIS data. FMX is unique only when combined with information on year and household.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[This is a 2-digit numeric variable with 0 implied decimal places]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="PX" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PX">
  <location EndPos="68" StartPos="67" width="2"/>
  <labl>Person number of respondent (from NHIS).</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PX is the original person number assigned to each individual by the NHIS. PX is unique only when combined with information on year, household, and family.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPX is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="PERWEIGHT" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PERWEIGHT">
  <location EndPos="80" StartPos="69" width="12"/>
  <labl>Final basic annual weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PERWEIGHT is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable based on the Final Annual Weight in the original NHIS public use files.  This weight should be used for many analyses at the person level, particularly with variables for which information was collected about all family members. PERWEIGHT represents the inverse probability of selection into the sample, adjusted for non-response with post-stratification adjustments for age, race/ethnicity, and sex using the Census Bureau's population control totals. For each year, the sum of these weights is equal to that year's civilian, non-institutionalized U.S. population.

There are instances, however, when the researcher should use a different person-level weight, particularly with supplements where a random adult or child family member was selected for questioning. For example, researchers analyzing variables from the sample adult/sample child supplements from 1997 forward should use SAMPWEIGHT rather than PERWEIGHT. 

Users  should review the documentation for extracted variables--most notably the "Weights" section toward the top of each variable description--to ascertain which weight is the appropriate choice for a given survey year. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPERWEIGHT is a 12-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SAMPWEIGHT" dcml="3" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SAMPWEIGHT">
  <location EndPos="92" StartPos="81" width="12"/>
  <labl>Sample Person Weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SAMPWEIGHT is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable that represents, with a few exceptions, the random selection of a sample person in the household to complete a supplement survey.  (The exceptions to this generalization are the 1983 health insurance supplement and 1993 health insurance, access to care, and family resources supplements, which were asked of all persons in the second half of the year.)

For survey years 1997 forward, SAMPWEIGHT is based on the Final Annual Sample Adult and Sample Child Weights in the original NHIS public use files. This weight should be used with variables taken from the sample adult or sample child supplements for 1997 on (as indicated by the supplement title in the "Source" section toward the top of each variable description). 

SAMPWEIGHT also contains the sampling weights for a subset of the pre-1997 supplements, for which the definition of a sample person, and the rules governing the selection of sample persons, are less consistent. The universe statements for SAMPWEIGHT document who was included in the supplements requiring use of this weight on a year-by-year basis. SAMPWEIGHT consistently represents the inverse probability of selection into a supplement, adjusted for non-response with additional post-stratification adjustments for age, race/ethnicity, and sex using the Census Bureau's population control totals.

Users should review the documentation for extracted variables--most notably the "Weights" section toward the top of each variable description--to ascertain which weight is the appropriate choice for a given survey year. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSAMPWEIGHT is a 12-digit numeric variable with three implied decimals. That is, values of 012345678912 should be interpreted as 12345678.912. The command files delivered with IPUMS extracts automatically divide SAMPWEIGHT by 1,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="FWEIGHT" dcml="6" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="FWEIGHT">
  <location EndPos="104" StartPos="93" width="12"/>
  <labl>Final annual family weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[FWEIGHT is a variable based on the Final Annual Weight in the original NHIS public use files. This weight should be used for many analyses at the family level, particularly with variables for which information was collected about family characteristics. 
&nbsp;Creating FWEIGHT requires using independent estimates of the number of families from a reliable source such as the U.S. Census Bureau in order to perform post-stratification adjustments in a manner similar to what was done for the person-level weights. However, such independent estimates do not exist. 

As a result, the NHIS used the "principle person" method to create family-level weights. The person weight with the smallest ratio adjustment within each family was used as a proxy for the family-level ratio adjustment. This method is believed to provide a more accurate estimate of the total number of U.S. families than either the use of other person weights within the family or the use of no ratio adjustments at all. Therefore, the Family weight contains factors for selection probabilities at the household level, household non-response adjustment, and several ratio adjustment factors that are applied to all person weights.Users should review the documentation for extracted variables--most notably the "Weights" section toward the top of each variable description--to ascertain which weight is the appropriate choice for a given survey year. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesFWEIGHT is a 6-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SUPP1WT" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SUPP1WT">
  <location EndPos="113" StartPos="105" width="9"/>
  <labl>Supplemental Person Weight 1</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SUPP1WT is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable that harmonizes the sampling weights for a select subset of the supplements of the original NHIS public use files.  In this case, harmonization refers to putting weights from various years and source supplement files into a single, consistently named variable. 

The majority of weights included in SUPP1WT come from the supplement surveys for childhood immunization (years 1992-2003), smoking (1978-1980), family medical expenses (1975-1976), and AIDS knowledge and attitudes (1987-1995). In some cases, SUPP1WT represents a randomly selected person from a household; for example, a sample person age 18 and older was selected for the 1990 AIDS supplement. In other cases, the survey was also administered to all persons within a specific age group; for example, the 1998 childhood immunization supplement was administered to a sample child under 18 plus all children age 12-35 months. SUPP1WT represents the inverse probability of selection into a supplement, adjusted for non-response with additional post-stratification adjustments for age, race/ethnicity, and sex using the Census Bureau's population control totals.

Beginning in 2011, the weights included in SUPP1WT are associated with variables from the Functioning and Disability supplement.

Users should review the documentation for extracted variables--most notably the "Weights" section toward the top of each variable description--to ascertain which weight is the appropriate choice for a given survey year. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSUPP1WT is a 9-digit-numeric variable.

0:	Not in Universe]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="ASTATFLG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="ASTATFLG">
  <location EndPos="114" StartPos="114" width="1"/>
  <labl>Sample adult flag</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[ASTATFLG identifies the record of a sample adult. A sample adult is the one person over age 18 per household who is randomly selected to complete the sample adult questionnaire. For 1997-2018, a sample adult is the one adult per family who was selected at random by the computerized survey instrument to answer additional health-related questions, under the survey design instituted in 1997.  All persons other than sample adults (those not having the value 1 in ASTATFLG) are coded as "not in universe" for variables derived from the additional questions asked only of sample adults.  (Some additional questions were asked of both sample adults and sample children.)  Every adult in each family, except for active duty armed forces members, was eligible to be selected as the sample adult.  

Prior to 2019, ASTATFLG has the value "no one selected as sample adult" (code 4) for all adults in the family in the following two cases: 1) sample adult status was incorrectly assigned to someone in the armed forces, or 2) it could not be ascertained which adult in the family was chosen as sample adult.   

For 2020 only, SALNGPRTFLG further distinguishes between sample adults included in the longitudinal sample and sample adults included in the partial sample. Please see the user note on COVID-related changes to the NHIS for more information on the longitudinal and partial samples.

A similar flag variable, CSTATFLG, identifies the record of a sample child.

This variable is automatically included in all extracts, but only has valid values for 1997 forward.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Sample adult, has record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Sample adult, no record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Not selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>No one selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Armed forces member</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>6</catValu>
    <labl>AF member, selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CSTATFLG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="CSTATFLG">
  <location EndPos="115" StartPos="115" width="1"/>
  <labl>Sample child flag</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[CSTATFLG identifies the record of a sample child. A sample child is the one person under age 18 per household who is randomly selected to complete the sample child questionnaire. For 1997-2018, the sample child is the one person under age 18 per family who was selected at random by the computerized survey instrument for additional health-related questions, under the survey design instituted in 1997. All persons other than sample children (those not having the value 1 in CSTATFLG) are coded as "not in universe" for variables derived from these additional questions asked only of sample children.  (Some additional questions were asked of both sample adults and sample children.)   

Prior to 2019, Every child in each family, except for active duty armed forces members and emancipated minors, was eligible to be selected as the sample child.  Emancipated minors are persons age 14 to 17 who are married or living with a partner OR who live on their own without the supervision of a parent, other adult family member, or legal guardian.  

CSTATFLG has the value "no one selected as sample child" (code 4) for all children in the family in the following two cases prior to 2019: 1) if sample child status was incorrectly assigned to someone who was ineligible, or 2) if it was unknown which child in the family was chosen as sample child.   

A similar flag variable, ASTATFLG, identifies the record of a sample adult.

This variable is automatically included in all extracts, but only has valid values for 1997 forward.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Sample child-has record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Sample child-no record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Not selected as sample child</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>No one selected as sample child</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Emancipated minor</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="AGE" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="AGE">
  <location EndPos="118" StartPos="116" width="3"/>
  <labl>Age</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[AGE reports the individual's age, in years since their last birthday. Starting in 2019, "Unknown-refused" and "Unknown-don't know" are allowed responses. Prior to 2019 age is not coded as "unknown" for any persons included in the IPUMS NHIS data. As the public use file's codebooks for 1998-2003 state, "Because age is an important variable for instrument check items and in developing the weights, all respondents must have data on age."]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesAGE is a 3-digit-numeric variable.

085:	Top code for 85 years or older (1963-1968 and 1997-forward)
090:	Top code for 90 years or older (1996 only)
099:	Top code for 99 years or older (1969-1995)
997:	Unknown-refused
998:	Unknown-not ascertained
999:	Unknown-don't know]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Core Demographic Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SEX" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SEX">
  <location EndPos="119" StartPos="119" width="1"/>
  <labl>Sex</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SEX indicates whether the person was male or female.  

Starting in 2019, "Unknown-refused" and "Unknown-don't know" responses are allowed. Prior to 2019, SEX is not coded as "unknown" for any persons included in the IPUMS NHIS data.

According to the 2020 Survey Description, for some variables, including SEX, the 2020 responses of sample adults that were part of the 2020 longitudinal sample were overwritten with their 2019 responses "to mitigate disclosure risks associated with differences in response from repeated measures among the same Sample Adults" (33). The sample adults' actual 2020 responses can be accessed through a Research Data Center (RDC). For more information on the 2020 longitudinal sample, please see SALNGPRTFLG.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Male</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Female</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Core Demographic Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="YRSINUSG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="YRSINUSG">
  <location EndPos="120" StartPos="120" width="1"/>
  <labl>Number of years spent in the U.S. (grouped year estimate)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample children and sample adults (or, prior to 2019, all persons) born outside the United States, YRSINUSG indicates how long they have been living in the United States.  In most cases, this information was collected via the question, "In what year did you come to the United States to stay?"  If the response to this question was "refused" or "don't know," the interviewer tried to collect the information via an alternatively phrased question: "About how long have you been in the United States?"   

The data included in the public use files for YRSINUSG are recodes of the responses to these questions, with each answer in the form of a calendar year converted to a number of years present.  The calendar year format of the initial question would have increased the precision of responses by discouraging rounding; the recoded format (number of years present) is easier for researchers to analyze. 

According to the 2020 Survey Description, for some variables, including YRSINUSG, the 2020 responses of sample adults that were part of the 2020 longitudinal sample were overwritten with their 2019 responses "to mitigate disclosure risks associated with differences in response from repeated measures among the same Sample Adults" (33). The sample adults' actual 2020 responses can be accessed through a Research Data Center (RDC). For more information on the 2020 longitudinal sample, please see SALNGPRTFLG.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Less than 1 year</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>1 year to less than 5 years</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>5 years to less than 10 years</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>10 years to less than 15 years</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>15 years or more</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CITIZEN" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="CITIZEN">
  <location EndPos="121" StartPos="121" width="1"/>
  <labl>U.S. citizenship</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For all sample children and sample adults who did not have a don't know, not ascertained, or refused response to whether they were born in the United States or a United States territory (USBORN), CITIZEN indicates whether the individual was a U.S. citizen. Prior to 2019, this variable was available for all persons.

According to the 2020 Survey Description, for some variables, including CITIZEN, the 2020 responses of sample adults that were part of the 2020 longitudinal sample were overwritten with their 2019 responses "to mitigate disclosure risks associated with differences in response from repeated measures among the same Sample Adults" (33). The sample adults' actual 2020 responses can be accessed through a Research Data Center (RDC). For more information on the 2020 longitudinal sample, please see SALNGPRTFLG.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No, not U.S. citizen</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, U.S. citizen</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="OCC" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="OCC">
  <location EndPos="123" StartPos="122" width="2"/>
  <labl>Detailed occupation </labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[OCC reports the sample person's primary occupation, coded into a contemporary Classified Index of Occupation (from 1969 to 1982) and the Standard Occupational Classification (from 1983 and forward). Please see the Comparability and Universe tabs for more information on how this variable was constructed. 

To increase comparability over time, the IPUMS NHIS provides OCC1995, which applies a common occupational classification system over time. This recoded variable is also discussed at the "User Note on Occupation and Industry Variables".]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl/>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HOURSWRK" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HOURSWRK">
  <location EndPos="125" StartPos="124" width="2"/>
  <labl>Total hours worked last week or usually</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18+ (and all persons age 18+ in 2004-2018) who worked at a paid or unpaid job or business last week, held a seasonal or contract position last week, or were not working last week because they were on vacation, on family/maternity leave, unable to work for health reasons, HOURSWRK reports the total hours that the sample person worked in the past week. or in the past two weeks at all jobs/ businesses or at the main job/business. The universe and time period for HOURSWRK were somewhat different for 1979 and 1991. HOURSWORK reports total hours worked in the past two weeks for sample persons aged 17+ in 1979 who, during the past 2 weeks, worked, had a job or business from which they were temporarily absent, or looked for work or were on layoff; in 1991, HOURSWORK reports total work hours worked in the  past two weeks for sample persons aged 18+ in 1991 who were employed in the past 2 weeks and worked for a private company or the federal, state, or local government. Please refer to the Universe and Comparability tabs for more information about changes in the universe, time period, and the types of jobs included in HOURSWRK.

Beginning in 2019, sample adults aged 18+ who held a seasonal or contract position last week continued to be identified by NCHS as included in the universe for HOURSWORK, but were omitted from the HOURSWRK question and had their responses set to "Unknown - Not Ascertained."]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>1</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>2</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>3</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>4</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>5</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>6</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>7</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>8</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>9</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>10</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>11</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>12</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>13</catValu>
    <labl>13</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>14</catValu>
    <labl>14</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>15</catValu>
    <labl>15</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>16</catValu>
    <labl>16</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>17</catValu>
    <labl>17</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>18</catValu>
    <labl>18</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>19</catValu>
    <labl>19</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>20</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>21</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>22</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>23</catValu>
    <labl>23</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>24</catValu>
    <labl>24</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>25</catValu>
    <labl>25</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>26</catValu>
    <labl>26</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>27</catValu>
    <labl>27</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>28</catValu>
    <labl>28</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>29</catValu>
    <labl>29</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>30</catValu>
    <labl>30</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>31</catValu>
    <labl>31</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>32</catValu>
    <labl>32</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>33</catValu>
    <labl>33</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>34</catValu>
    <labl>34</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>35</catValu>
    <labl>35</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>36</catValu>
    <labl>36</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>37</catValu>
    <labl>37</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>38</catValu>
    <labl>38</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>39</catValu>
    <labl>39</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>40</catValu>
    <labl>40</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>41</catValu>
    <labl>41</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>42</catValu>
    <labl>42</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>43</catValu>
    <labl>43</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>44</catValu>
    <labl>44</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>45</catValu>
    <labl>45</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>46</catValu>
    <labl>46</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>47</catValu>
    <labl>47</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>48</catValu>
    <labl>48</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>49</catValu>
    <labl>49</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>50</catValu>
    <labl>50</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>51</catValu>
    <labl>51</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>52</catValu>
    <labl>52</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>53</catValu>
    <labl>53</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>54</catValu>
    <labl>54</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>55</catValu>
    <labl>55</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>56</catValu>
    <labl>56</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>57</catValu>
    <labl>57</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>58</catValu>
    <labl>58</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>59</catValu>
    <labl>59</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>60</catValu>
    <labl>60</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>61</catValu>
    <labl>61</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>62</catValu>
    <labl>62</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>63</catValu>
    <labl>63</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>64</catValu>
    <labl>64</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>65</catValu>
    <labl>65</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>66</catValu>
    <labl>66</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>67</catValu>
    <labl>67</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>68</catValu>
    <labl>68</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>69</catValu>
    <labl>69</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>70</catValu>
    <labl>70</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>71</catValu>
    <labl>71</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>72</catValu>
    <labl>72</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>73</catValu>
    <labl>73</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>74</catValu>
    <labl>74</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>75</catValu>
    <labl>75</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>76</catValu>
    <labl>76</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>77</catValu>
    <labl>77</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>78</catValu>
    <labl>78</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>79</catValu>
    <labl>79</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>80</catValu>
    <labl>80</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>81</catValu>
    <labl>81</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>82</catValu>
    <labl>82</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>83</catValu>
    <labl>83</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>84</catValu>
    <labl>84</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>85</catValu>
    <labl>85</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>86</catValu>
    <labl>86</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>87</catValu>
    <labl>87</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>88</catValu>
    <labl>88</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>89</catValu>
    <labl>89</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>90</catValu>
    <labl>90</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>91</catValu>
    <labl>91</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>92</catValu>
    <labl>92</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>93</catValu>
    <labl>93</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>94</catValu>
    <labl>94</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>95</catValu>
    <labl>95+ hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown--don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="WRKARRNG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="WRKARRNG">
  <location EndPos="126" StartPos="126" width="1"/>
  <labl>Work arrangement</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample persons aged 18 and older who are currently employed or were employed at some point in the past 12 months, WRKARRNG reports the sample person's work arrangement. Respondents are given a list of 6 categories to choose from. Please refer to the codes tab for more information.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Independent contractor or freelancer</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>On-call, work when called to work</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Paid by temporary agency</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Worked for contractor who provides workers under contract</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Regular, standard employee</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>6</catValu>
    <labl>Other</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CHOLHIGHYR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="CHOLHIGHYR">
  <location EndPos="127" StartPos="127" width="1"/>
  <labl>Had high cholesterol, past 12 months</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults, and sample children ages 6-17 in 2012, CHOLHIGHYR indicates whether the person had high cholesterol during the past 12 months. In all years except for 2013, this question was asked only of those who were ever told they have high cholesterol (CHOLHIGHEV). Please see Comparability and Universe tabs for changes in the universe between samples.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Condition Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HYPERTENYR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HYPERTENYR">
  <location EndPos="128" StartPos="128" width="1"/>
  <labl>Had hypertension, past 12 months</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HYPERTENYR indicates whether persons had hypertension or high blood pressure during the past 12 months.  In 1977, this information was collected for all persons age 20 and older; in 2002 and 2007, it was collected only from sample adults age 18+ who were ever diagnosed by a doctor or other health professional as having hypertension (HYPERTENEV); in 2012 sample children ages 6-17 were also included. Beginning in 2013, it was collected from sample adults age 18+ who were ever told they had hypertension and were told they had hypertension on two or more different visits to a health professional (HYP2TIME).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Condition Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CHOLMEDNOW" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="CHOLMEDNOW">
  <location EndPos="129" StartPos="129" width="1"/>
  <labl>Now taking prescribed medicine to lower cholesterol</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults who were ever told they have high cholesterol (CHOLHIGHEV), CHOLMEDNOW indicates if they currently take prescribed medication to lower their cholesterol level.

In 1991, 1993, 1998, and 2015-2018, CHOLMEDNOW indicates if sample adults who were ever prescribed medicine for high cholesterol (CHOLMEDPRE) are currently taking medication to lower their cholesterol level. In 2005, CHOLMEDNOW indicates if sample adults, regardless of whether they had been told they have high cholesterol, currently takes prescribed medication regularly, that is, at least 3 times a week, to lower their cholesterol level.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">High Cholesterol Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HYPMEDNOW" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HYPMEDNOW">
  <location EndPos="130" StartPos="130" width="1"/>
  <labl>Now taking prescribed medicine to lower blood pressure</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For adults who were diagnosed or treated for high blood pressure (or, in 1989, for adults with confirmed diabetes), HYPMEDNOW reports if the person is currently taking medicine prescribed by a doctor to lower blood pressure. Please see Comparability and Universe tabs for information on changes in universe between samples.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Hypertension Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SMOKESTATUS2" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SMOKESTATUS2">
  <location EndPos="132" StartPos="131" width="2"/>
  <labl>Cigarette smoking recode 2: Current detailed/former/never</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults 18 and over, this is a recoded variable indicating the respondent's current smoking status in categories of current smoker, every day current smoker, some day current smoker, current smoker--unknown frequency of smoking, and also indicates former smoker, never smoked and "has smoked, current smoking status unknown."
&nbsp;In this variable, current smokers were divided into "every day" smokers or "some days" smokers.  The process to classify respondents into these categories changed slightly between 1991 and 1992 forward.  In 1991, ever smokers were asked if they smoke now; respondents who said "yes" were asked if they smoked "every day" or "some days.  Respondents who answered "no" were asked, "Do you smoke some days or not at all?" This additional follow-up resulted in the classification of persons as "someday smokers" who would otherwise have been considered former smokers, since they initially said that they did not smoke now. 

In 1992, questions on smoking status were included in two sections of the survey; in the  Cancer Control section, the same three questions from in the 1991 questionnaire were used; in the Cancer Epidemiology section, just two questions were used: "Have you smoked at least 100 cigarettes during your entire life?" If yes, "Do you NOW smoke cigarettes every day, some days, or not at all?" Use of both sets of questions allowed for estimation of the impact of the question change on population prevalence. The revised current smoking status question was estimated to have resulted in an increase in smoking prevalence of about 1 percent-- a result occurring mainly from capturing smoking among persons who would otherwise have been classified as nonsmokers with the original question.

This version of the question was used from 1992 forward.Related Variables]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>Current smoker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>Current every day smoker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>Current some day smoker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>13</catValu>
    <labl>Current smoker, unknown how often smokes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>Former smoker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>30</catValu>
    <labl>Never smoked</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>40</catValu>
    <labl>Has smoked, current smoking status unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>90</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown if ever smoked</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Smoking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MOD10FWK" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="MOD10FWK">
  <location EndPos="134" StartPos="133" width="2"/>
  <labl>Frequency of moderate activity 10+ minutes: Times per week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[MOD10FWK is a recoded variable created by the staff at the National Center for Health Statistics that draws upon the information in MOD10FTP (Frequency of moderate activity 10+ minutes: Time period) and MOD10FNO (Frequency of moderate activity 10+ minutes: Number of units) and reports the frequency of light or moderate leisure-time physical activities in terms of a single time unit, times per week. Prior to 2020, the survey text for MOD10FNO and MOD10FTP inquired specifically about exercise that lasted at least 10 minutes. Beginning in 2020, the question did not include this provision.

Light or moderate activities are described in the survey question itself as activities that "cause only light sweating or a slight to moderate increase in breathing or heart rate."  The Field Representative's Manualprovides examples of light or moderate leisure-time physical activities, although these examples were not routinely shared with respondents.  These examples include leisurely walking or bicycling, slow swimming or dancing, and simple gardening.

According to the Field Representative's Manuals for 2001-2018, the maximum frequency of each broad category of physical activity (moderate activity, vigorous activity, strengthening activities, and stretching activities) was topcoded at 4 times per day (or its equivalent in some other time unit). Beginning in 2020, individuals with values of 4 times per day (or its equivalent) or greater were coded as "93 - Extreme value."

For general discussion of how and why the NHIS collected information on adult physical activity for 1997 forward, see VIG10FNO.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesMOD10FWK is a 2-digit-numeric variable.

00:	Not in Universe
93:	Extreme value
94:	Less than once per week
95:	Never
96:	Unable to do this activity
97:	Unknown-refused
98:	Unknown-not ascertained
99:	Unknown-don't know]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Physical Activity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="VIG10FWK" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="VIG10FWK">
  <location EndPos="136" StartPos="135" width="2"/>
  <labl>Frequency of vigorous activity 10+ minutes: Times per week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[VIG10FWK is a recoded variable created by the staff at the National Center for Health Statistics that draws upon the information in VIG10FTP (Frequency of vigorous activity 10+ minutes: Time period) and VIG10FNO (Frequency of vigorous activity 10+ minutes: Number of units) and reports the frequency of vigorous leisure-time physical activities in terms of a single time unit, times per week. Prior to 2020, the survey text for VIG10FNO and VIG10FTP inquired specifically about exercise that lasted at least 10 minutes. Beginning in 2020, the question did not include this provision.

Vigorous leisure-time activities are described in the survey question itself as activities that "cause heavy sweating or large increases in breathing or heart rate."  The Field Representative's Manual provides examples of vigorous activities, although these examples were not routinely shared with respondents.  These examples include fast walking, fast bicycling, jogging, strenuous swimming or sports play, vigorous aerobic dance, and strenuous gardening.

According to the Field Representative's Manuals for 2001-2018, the maximum frequency of each broad category of physical activity (moderate activity, vigorous activity, strengthening activities, and stretching activities) was topcoded at 4 times per day (or its equivalent in some other time unit). Beginning in 2020, individuals with values of 4 times per day (or its equivalent) or greater were coded as "93 - Extreme value."

For general discussion of how and why the NHIS collected information on adult physical activity for 1997 forward, see VIG10FNO.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[Codes00: Not in Universe
93: Extreme value
94: Less than once per week
95: Never
96: Unable to do moderate/vigorous activity
97: Unknown-refused
98: Unknown-not ascertained
99: Unknown-don't know]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Physical Activity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="STRONGFWK" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="STRONGFWK">
  <location EndPos="138" StartPos="137" width="2"/>
  <labl>Frequency of strengthening activity: Times per week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[STRONGFWK is a recoded variable created by the staff at the National Center for Health Statistics that draws upon the information in STRONGFTP (Frequency of strengthening activity: Time period) and STRONGFNO (Frequency of strengthening activity: Number of units) and reports the frequency of strengthening leisure-time physical activities in terms of a single time unit, times per week.

Definitions

Leisure-time strengthening activities are described in the survey question itself as activities "specifically designed to strengthen your muscles such as lifting weights or doing calisthenics."
&nbsp;The Field Representative's Manual provides other examples of strengthening activities, although these examples were not routinely shared with respondents.  These examples include "activities that require strenuous muscle contractions," such as resistance training, push-ups, and sit-ups.Data Collection]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSTRONGFWK is a 2-digit-numeric variable.

00:	Not in Universe
93:	Extreme value
94:	Less than once per week
95:	Never
96:	Unable to do this activity
97:	Unknown-refused
98:	Unknown-not ascertained
99:	Unknown-don't know]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Physical Activity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HRSLEEP" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HRSLEEP">
  <location EndPos="140" StartPos="139" width="2"/>
  <labl>Usual hours sleep per day</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults, HRSLEEP reports how many hours, on average, the respondent sleeps per day. For surveys prior to 2004, interviewers were instructed to write down responses verbatim.  From 2004 forward, interviewers were instructed to report the hours of sleep in whole numbers, rounding values of 30 minutes or more UP to the nearest hour or otherwise rounding down. IPUMS NHIS recodes the values from the earlier surveys into whole number values, following the same rules as 2004 forward.

Beginning in 2020, HRSLEEP is one of a set of rotating core variables on sleep duration and quality collected by the NHIS every other year. In addition to HRSLEEP, other variables in the sleep rotating core include:

Sample Adults
SLEEPRESTFRQ: How often woke up feeling well rested, past 30 days

SLEEPFALLFRQ: How often had trouble falling asleep, past 30 days

SLEEPSTAYFRQ: How often had trouble staying asleep, past 30 days

SLEEPMEDFRQ: How often took medication for sleep, past 30 days
Sample Children
CSLEEPREST: How often wake up feeling well rested in a typical school week

CSLEEPGETUP: How often difficult to get out of bed in the morning in a typical school week

CSLEEPTIRED: How often complain of being tired during the day in a typical school week

CSLEEPNAPS: How often nap or fall asleep during the day in a typical school week

CSLEEPBEDTIME: How often have a regular bedtime on school nights in a typical school week

CSLEEPWKTIME: How often wake up at same time in a typical school week
Related Variables on Sleep&nbsp;A set of questions on sleep were asked annually of sample adults in 2004-2018 that are similar to those asked beginning in 2020 but differ in the reference period (past week vs. past 30 days) and the structure of the response categories (number of days in past week vs. how often in the past 30 days). These variables include:

SLEEPREST: Days woke up feeling rested, past week

SLEEPFALL: Number of times having trouble falling asleep, past week

SLEEPSTAY: Number of times having trouble staying asleep, past week

SLEEPMEDS: Number of times taking medication for sleep, past week
]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>1 hour (1990: 0 or 1 hour)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>2 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>3 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>4 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>5 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>6 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>7 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>8 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>9 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>10 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>11 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>12 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>13</catValu>
    <labl>13 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>14</catValu>
    <labl>14 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>15</catValu>
    <labl>15 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>16</catValu>
    <labl>16 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>17</catValu>
    <labl>17 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>18</catValu>
    <labl>18 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>19</catValu>
    <labl>19 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>20 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>21 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>22 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>23</catValu>
    <labl>23 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>24</catValu>
    <labl>24 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>25</catValu>
    <labl>Less than 1 hour</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SLEEPFALL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SLEEPFALL">
  <location EndPos="142" StartPos="141" width="2"/>
  <labl>Number of times having trouble falling asleep, past week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18 and older, SLEEPFALL reports how often they had trouble falling asleep in the past week. This variable was included as a core item in the Adult Supplemental Items (ASI) section of the Sample Adult questionnaire, introduced in 2013.

Related Variables
Other sleep-related variables included in the ASI section include: SLEEPSTAY (number of times had trouble staying asleep, past week), SLEEPMEDS (number of times taking sleep medication, past week), and SLEEPREST (days woke up feeling rested, past week).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Did not have trouble falling asleep past week</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>7 or more times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SLEEPSTAY" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SLEEPSTAY">
  <location EndPos="144" StartPos="143" width="2"/>
  <labl>Number of times having trouble staying asleep, past week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18 and older, SLEEPSTAY reports how often they had trouble staying asleep in the past week. This variable was included as a core item in the Adult Supplemental Items (ASI) section of the Sample Adult questionnaire, introduced in 2013.

Related Variables
For a list of other sleep-related variables included in the ASI section, refer to SLEEPFALL.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Did not have trouble staying asleep past week</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>One time</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Two times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>Three times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>Four times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>Five times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>Six times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>7 or more times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SLEEPMEDS" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SLEEPMEDS">
  <location EndPos="146" StartPos="145" width="2"/>
  <labl>Number of times taking medication for sleep, past week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18 and older, SLEEPMEDS reports how often they used medication to help them fall or stay asleep in the past week. This variable was included as a core item in the Adult Supplemental Items (ASI) section of the Sample Adult questionnaire, introduced in 2013.

Related Variables
For a list of other sleep-related variables included in the ASI section, refer to SLEEPFALL.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Did not take medication to help sleep in past week</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>7 or more times</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SLEEPREST" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="SLEEPREST">
  <location EndPos="148" StartPos="147" width="2"/>
  <labl>Days woke up feeling rested, past week</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18 and older, SLEEPREST reports how many days they woke up feeling well rested in the past week. This variable was included as a core item in the Adult Supplemental Items (ASI) section of the Sample Adult questionnaire, introduced in 2013.

Related Variables
For a list of other sleep-related variables included in the ASI section, refer to SLEEPFALL.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Never felt rested this past week</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Sleep Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="TIREFREQ3MO" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="TIREFREQ3MO">
  <location EndPos="149" StartPos="149" width="1"/>
  <labl>Frequency of feeling exhausted in last 3 months</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults, TIREFREQ3MO reports how often, in the past three months, they felt very tired or exhausted.

Beginning in 2020, TIREFREQ3MO is one of a set of rotating core variables on fatigue, collected every other year. The fatigue rotating core variables were also collected in previous years, as part of the Adult Functioning and Disability supplement (2011-2017) and sample adult questionnaire (2018). In addition to TIREFREQ3MO, the fatigue rotating core variables include:

TIREDURALAST: Duration of exhaustion, last time

TIREFEELEVL: Level of exhaustion, last time had exhaustion
Also beginning in 2020, the NHIS collected a rotating core set of variables on sleep duration and quality. Please see HRSLEEP for more information about the sleep rotating core.

The NHIS also collected several additional variables on fatigue as part of the 2010 Quality of Life supplement:

TIREFEELCLAR: Clarification of in-between amount of exhaustion

TIREYWORKEX: Reason exhausted: Too much work or exercise

TIREYNOTSLEP: Reason exhausted: Not getting enough sleep

TIREYHEALTH: Reason exhausted: Physical or health-related problem

TIREYOTHER: Reason exhausted: Something else
]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Never</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Some days</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Most days</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Every day</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Fatigue Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="TIREDURALAST" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="TIREDURALAST">
  <location EndPos="150" StartPos="150" width="1"/>
  <labl>Duration of exhaustion, last time</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults who felt very tired or exhausted some days, most days, every day, or don't know or refused to say how often they felt exhausted (TIREFREQ3MO), TIREDURALAST reports the duration of their exhaustion the last time they felt exhausted. 

Beginning in 2020, TIREDURALAST is one of a set of rotating core variables on fatigue, collected every other year. For more information on the fatigue rotating core variables or about fatigue variables available in the NHIS prior to 2020, please see (TIREFREQ3MO).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Some of the day</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Most of the day</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>All of the day</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Fatigue Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="TIREFEELEVL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="TIREFEELEVL">
  <location EndPos="151" StartPos="151" width="1"/>
  <labl>Level of exhaustion, last time had exhaustion</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults who felt very tired or exhausted some days, most days, every day, or don't know or refused to say how often they felt exhausted (TIREFREQ3MO), TIREFEELEVL reports the level of exhaustion they felt, the last time they felt exhausted. 

Beginning in 2020, TIREDURALAST is one of a set of rotating core variables on fatigue, collected every other year. For more information on the fatigue rotating core variables or about fatigue variables available in the NHIS prior to 2020, please see (TIREFREQ3MO).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>A little</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>A lot</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Somewhere between a little and a lot</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Fatigue Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MORTSTAT" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="MORTSTAT">
  <location EndPos="152" StartPos="152" width="1"/>
  <labl>Final mortality status</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For persons aged 18 and older included in the 1986-2014 NHIS samples and sample adults 18 and older included in the 2015-2018 NHIS samples who provided sufficient data for linking (MORTELIG), MORTSTAT reports the final vital status (assumed alive or assumed deceased). For more information about the methodology to link NHIS records to the NDI, please see the  NCHS report on the NHIS-NDI linkage methods and analytic considerations.

MORTSTAT is one of a set of mortality variables released by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) as part of the 2019 Linked Mortality File (LMF) update. The 2019 LMF includes mortality information for participants in the 1986-2018 NHIS samples with mortality follow up in the NDI through December 31, 2019. For more information on the LMF, including which variables it offers and the appropriate sampling weights to use when analyzing the mortality data, see the description tab of MORTELIG.

For further information on the NDI and the creation of the mortality variables, see the variable description for MORTELIG and the technical documents from NCHS on the creation and analysis of the NHIS Linked Mortality Files.

Related Variables
For a list of all mortality variables from the LMF included in the IPUMS NHIS, please refer to the MORTELIG variable description.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Assumed deceased</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Assumed alive</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Mortality Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MORTUCODLD" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="MORTUCODLD">
  <location EndPos="154" StartPos="153" width="2"/>
  <labl>Leading underlying cause of death (ICD-10)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For persons aged 18 and older included in the 1986-2014 NHIS samples and sample adults aged 18 and older included in the 2015-2018 NHIS samples who provided sufficient data for linking (MORTELIG) and whose final vital status was judged deceased (MORTSTAT) as of December 31, 2019, MORTUCODLD reports the leading underlying cause of death. For more information about the methodology to link NHIS records to the NDI, please see the  NCHS report on the NHIS-NDI linkage methods and analytic considerations. For survey respondents in the 2005 or later surveys and decedents who died after December 2006, MORTUCODLD is the most detailed information available on the linked NHIS-NDI public use files about underlying cause of death. For access to the detailed cause of death codes available on the linked NHIS-NDI restricted access files, see documentation on the restricted version of the NHIS Linked Mortality Files.

MORTUCODLD is a recode created by NCHS to classify underlying cause of death into 10 categories. Deaths that occurred prior to 1999 are coded based on the 9th revision of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases, Injuries, and Causes of Death (ICD-9). Deaths that occurred from 1999 forward were coded based on the 10th revision of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases, Injuries, and Causes of Death (ICD-10). In sample years 2015 forward, eligible respondents are limited to a single sample adult per household. Because of the smaller sample size, NCHS has grouped people with MORTUCODLD codes of 5-9 into code 10 (All other causes - residual) to lower the risk of respondent identification. Please see the Public-use Linked Mortality File Readme for information about these codes.

MORTUCODLD is one of a set of mortality variables released by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) as part of the 2019 Linked Mortality File (LMF) update. The 2019 LMF includes mortality information for participants in the 1986-2018 NHIS samples with mortality follow up in the NDI through December 31, 2019. For more information on the LMF, including which variables it offers and the appropriate sampling weights to use when analyzing the mortality data, see the description tab of MORTELIG.

Related Variables
For a list of all mortality variables from the LMF included in the IPUMS NHIS, please refer to the MORTELIG variable description.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Diseases of heart</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Malignant neoplasms</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>Chronic lower respiratory diseases</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>Accidents (unintentional injuries)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>Cerebrovascular diseases</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>Alzheimer's disease</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>Diabetes mellitus</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>Influenza and pneumonia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>Nephritis, nephrotic syndrome and nephrosis</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>All other causes (residual)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Mortality Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MORTHYPR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="MORTHYPR">
  <location EndPos="155" StartPos="155" width="1"/>
  <labl>Hypertension flag from multiple cause of death (MCOD)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For persons ages 18 and older included in the 1986-2014 NHIS samples and sample adults 18 and older included in the 2015-2018 NHIS samples who provided sufficient data for linking (MORTELIG) and whose final vital status was judged deceased (MORTSTAT) as of December 31, 2019. MORTHYPR indicates whether, in addition to the underlying cause of death (MORTUCODLD), hypertension was listed as a contributing cause of death. For more information about the methodology to link NHIS records to the NDI, please see the  the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) report on the NHIS-NDI linkage methods and analytic considerations. Hypertension was classified based on an ICD-9 code of 401 or 403 for 1986-1998 and on an ICD-10 code of I10 or I12 for 1999 forward.

MORTHYPR is one of a set of mortality variables released by the NCHS as part of the Linked Mortality File (LMF) update. The LMF includes mortality information for participants in the 1986-2018 NHIS samples with mortality follow up in the NDI through December 31, 2019. For more information on the LMF, including which variables it offers and the appropriate sampling weights to use when analyzing the mortality data, see the description tab of MORTELIG. For more information on LMFs in general, see the IPUMS user note about the NHIS-LMFs. 

Related Variables&nbsp;MORTHYPR was one of three multiple cause of death flags that indicate whether specific health conditions were listed as contributing causes of death (in addition to the underlying cause of death). MORTDIAB indicates whether diabetes was listed as a contributing cause of death; MORTHIPFX, not available for NHIS participants in the 2005-forward surveys or for decedents who died after December 2006, indicates whether hip fracture was listed as a contributing cause of death.

For a list of all mortality variables from the LMF included in the IPUMS NHIS, please refer to the MORTELIG variable description.

For further information on the NDI and the creation of the mortality variables, see the variable description for MORTELIG and the technical documents from NCHS on the creation and analysis of the NHIS Linked Mortality Files.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Mortality Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MORTWTSA" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="MORTWTSA">
  <location EndPos="163" StartPos="156" width="8"/>
  <labl>Sample adult weight adjusted for ineligible respondents in mortality analysis</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults aged 18 and older included in the 1997-2018 samples, MORTWTSA reports the sampling weight that adjusts for ineligible respondents in analyses of data linking NHIS participants during survey years 1997 to 2018 to the National Death Index (NDI) with mortality follow up through December 31, 2019. Because of changes in the universe of NHIS participants linked to the NDI, that is, included in the Linked Mortality File (LMF) data, this is the only sampling weight available for use in mortality analyses including participants in the 2015 and later NHIS samples.

Because adult survey participants who provided insufficient data for linking may differ from those who provided enough data for linking, ignoring the ineligible adult respondents could lead to biased mortality analysis. To correct this bias, the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) developed the eligibility-adjusted weights for use with variables in the 2019 LMF update. MORTWTSA is a mortality weight designed for use with sample adult variables and is available for the NHIS years 1997-2018. (A similar variable, MORTWT, is appropriate for weighting variables from the NHIS person files in conjunction with mortality variables and is available for the NHIS years 1986-2014).  

When analyzing NHIS variables from the sample adult files in conjunction with any of the mortality variables, users should employ MORTWTSA rather than the sample adult weight (SAMPWEIGHT). SAMPWEIGHT is based on the Final Annual Sample Adult Weights (for survey years 1997 forward) in the original NHIS public use files.

MORTWTSA is one of a set of mortality variables released by the NCHS as part of the 2019 LMF update. The 2019 LMF includes mortality information for participants in the 1986-2018 NHIS samples with mortality follow up in the NDI through December 31, 2019. For more information on the LMF, including which variables it offers and the appropriate sampling weights to use when analyzing the mortality data, see the description tab of MORTELIG. 
Related Variables
For a list of all mortality variables from the LMF included in the IPUMS NHIS, please refer to the MORTELIG variable description.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesMORTWTSA is a variable with eight columns and no implied decimals.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Mortality Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
</dataDscr>
</codeBook>
